This is how to draw a cross-section of a
mitochondrion. First thing you need to
know is mitochondria live inside other
cells. They're kind of like a cell
within a cell because very early on in
the evolution of life, an ancestor cell
to this mitochondrion got eaten by
another cell, but then didn't get
digested. Instead, the cells started
working together. I give you food, you
give me energy. That's why people call
mitochondria the powerhouse of the cell,
and it was very successful as pretty
much every cell in plants, animals, and
fungi have got mitochondria in them.
They've got a smooth outer membrane and
a wiggly inner membrane. These folds are
called cristae, and they help the inner
membrane have a large surface area
because this is where all the energy
generation happens. This inner membrane
is studded with these things called ATP
synthase particles, which is a key part
of the energy creation. It basically
drives the creation of ATP, which is the
main energy-carrying molecule in cells.
Inside the inner membrane is a gel-like
fluid called the matrix, which contains
hundreds of enzymes which break down the
nutrients that come in. These metabolic
processes also use oxygen, which is why
red blood cells don't have mitochondria
in them as they would just suck up all
the oxygen the red blood cells are
trying to transport around the body. We
also have ribosomes, the protein
builders in the mitochondria, and
granules, which regulate the speed of
the metabolism in the mitochondria. And
finally, we need to draw mitochondrial
DNA, which is completely different to
the DNA of the host cell. Interestingly,
we inherit our mitochondrial DNA only
from our mothers, and this DNA allows
the mitochondrion to self-replicate
within cells, kind of similar how to
bacteria reproduce. So, that's how to
draw mitochondria. How cute are they?